[Music]
hey folks welcome to this very special
Independence Day Dark Horse podcast live
stream I am with my favorite Patriot dr.
Heather hang we have a lot planned for
today if all goes well with the dialogue
a little later we are going to bring out
some British friends of ours and shoot
muskets at them so there's a lot in
store I guess I'm not sure it's tough at
first but she's she she maybe both of
our favorite Patriot yeah that's that's
that's good she's a very patriotic dog
mm-hmm all right so we should be talking
today about what America is and what it
is becoming you game sure let's do it
all right so I want to start this in an
odd place the country was obviously
founded well before Darwin had written
the Origin of Species and a century or
more before we understood cultural
evolution well enough to see ourselves
through an evolutionary lens but I do
think there's an important evolutionary
take that we all need to have America is
a very special country based on what it
was founded to do but there's too much
focus on the Constitution the
Constitution is an important document
it's essential to this unique purpose
but the purpose is never really stated
human beings like other organisms are
built to compete on the basis of their
genetic relatedness the United States is
first and foremost a grouping of people
who are not related closely to each
other and the Constitution is a document
designed to stabilize that strategy all
of the the content of the Constitution
is built to take the conflicts of
interest and other things that would
tend to make an attempt to group people
who are not genetically related to each
other it is an attempt to make those
structures stable so that is to say that
under normal circumstances evolution has
one group competing against another
based on who is closely related to whom
in the United States an attempt was made
to do something else and that was to
take the idea of reciprocity which is
itself an evolutionary concept and to
make it structurally sound such that we
could continue on indefinitely profiting
not so much from collaborating with
those who are closely related to us but
collaborating with those who have a
shared interest and it is a beautiful
concept it is a concept so good that it
has been highly contagious and I think
we are all noticing now that as we look
out across the world we are seeing our
protests spread across oceans even
though some of the things that are being
complained about aren't necessarily
distributed across the oceans in this
way there's something almost incoherent
about the idea of Nations because across
the West so much that resides in our
national character has actually caught
on because other parts of the world have
discovered just how good it is to put
genetic relatedness aside and to
collaborate based on other things so my
concern about the present is that what
we are facing is a revolt against the
very core concept at the heart of what
this nation is and that the results of
that revolt are going to predictably
bump us back into a prior state of being
one in which people look at other people
with suspicions based on how distantly
related they may be and that seems to me
to be a disaster and one that we should
be considering especially on
Independence Day beautiful so just to
add a tiny bit of flesh to the concept
of reciprocity which you invoked I would
say that the you know the golden rule as
outlined in the New Testament presumably
we imagine from Jesus first advocates
for us to extend our trust and and
goodness networks beyond that of kin
even to strangers right and that is of
course a kind of direct reciprocity to
use the language of evolutionary biology
but then we have you know people were
doing this
before it was named by evolutionary
biologists in the 70s and 80s but then
we have a form of indirect reciprocity
in which it is exactly as you say more
distributed and this is indeed you know
what was named in the I can't remember
exactly when 60 70s 80s the concept of
indirect reciprocity was exactly what
some of the at least some of and maybe
all of the founding fathers of this
country were basing their their
documents on the idea that we could
actually come together without without a
shared history in the past but with a
shared fate going forward you know it's
funny I was wondering whether or not to
point out this connection myself I'm
glad you did hmm
you're right there is something in the
founding character of the country that I
think we have to admit is actually
derived from the Christian roots of the
founders now of course those Christian
roots were themselves derived from
Jewish roots and the beautiful thing
about them is that once you say to your
population hey let's put genetic
relatedness aside and let's collaborate
based on something else it's capable of
spreading outside that population to an
arbitrarily large group potentially to
the whole world and it also allows for
the borrowing of ideas outside of the
group to which you say you belong or
that you actually belong a hundred
percent so in if we were to take this to
economic terms what we would say is that
the generation of wealth that is
facilitated by putting genetic
relatedness aside is massive and more
than compensates you for what you lose
by giving up on viewing the world
through this lens so in some sense Jesus
the radical Jewish rabbi as I like to
think of him was advocating for this
sidelining of genes there's a strong
argument to be made that you see this
tendency evolved in many places in fact
there's a rabbit rabbi hillel version is
about the same time as Jesus obviously
Buddhists have taken this to an extreme
so we see this concept emerging all over
the place and you would expect that
because it's so profitable to put
genetic relatedness aside
what you get is is fantastic and
incredible far beyond economic
profitability yes I mean profitable in
flourishes and human flourishing manner
and so it's not just the Golden Rule
I think this is also contained in the
story of the Good Samaritan elf right
and the basic idea is hey in all of
these cases it's not like the
relatedness doesn't exist I mean the
tribes are very directly invoked in the
story of the Good Samaritan but the
point is that is not a bar to
cooperation so there is this concept
dragged into our documents and then
there is what we would now call game
theory in those documents wouldn't have
been called that then so you've got
evolution and game theory that are built
in because there was a keen awareness
amongst these very sophisticated
thinkers of their day that it wasn't
enough just simply to say hey this is a
good idea right you have to build
something that stabilizes it so you know
if we were to translate that into
scientific language I would say they
were looking for an evolutionarily
stable strategy though they wouldn't
have known to think of it in those terms
and they didn't find one they found
something that was quite durable but we
are now watching what takes it apart and
well I mean they were explicitly looking
for something that avoided tyranny right
that that could stop tyranny and its
tracks could see it soon early enough
that it would stop it
but even so Jefferson says that
revolution will be necessary every now
and again he he he does not think that
they have come upon a strategy so stable
not to use his words again but he does
not think that they've come upon an
evolutionary stable strategy that is
infinite into the future he hopes that
it will it will go into the future for
long enough that that there will be more
insight by the time changes are
necessary so are you thinking of the
tree of liberty you must periodically be
refreshed with the blood of patriots and
tyrants I do not remember I can I can
try to find it I can try to find the
quote I'm thinking of because I'm not
sure if that if that set my tripod isn't
working I'm not sure if that quote is
intended to suggest revolution or not
but it is certainly a warning that the
system is not understood to be perfectly
stable in its own right and that it will
it will necessarily require vigilance
and risk-taking by people in the future
in order to protect it and likewise
Benjamin Franklin's statement a republic
if you can keep it and I've begun to
think of this now as a republic if you
can save it at this point I think we're
headed towards a different fate and that
those of us who get what we stand to
lose should think of it in these terms
that effectively this is the moment that
Franklin was warning us about and the
question is do we have what it takes to
save this beautiful experiment but it
does mean that we should be having a
conversation about what happens if we
don't because the reason that we must
save it is contained in what happens if
we don't save it and I don't think there
has been nearly enough public discussion
of that that will reach the right people
you have something you wanted to the
computer isn't really working from him
I'm unable to find what I was looking
for I find from the collected papers but
I can't figure out where I was quoting
from even in a democracy or in a
democracy rebellion need to happen with
some regularity I'm paraphrasing him
here and a piece that I've published on
college presidents a couple years ago
but my citation is just from his
collected papers so I'm not sure where
it is all right well let's put it aside
the quote about the tree of Liberty I
think will will do for the moment it's
not exactly sure it's not exactly clear
what is being referred to
except that one should not imagine that
this thing once said on autopilot is
going to continue on indefinitely
without without bravery and patriotism
to defend it and and we should to be
clear an evolutionarily stable strategy
isn't one that is inherently static
right this this is easily misunderstood
stability is easily misunderstood for
stasis and unchanging this but a
strategy itself can respond to different
inputs in different but predictable ways
yeah in fact I would argue and this is a
great lesson from parenting as well as a
nation-building is a static strategy is
certain to fail ultimately because there
will be
cracks in it defects and those things
will be exploited by anything that has
time to figure out how to do it so what
you need a strategy that's dynamic
enough to become anti fragile another
term that the founders didn't know that
is at the heart of what they were
attempting to do so um I had thought
that maybe we would talk a little bit
about what it is like to be an American
at this moment how it compares to what
it has been like in the past and where
we might be headed all right so I want
to start by talking about what it is
like to collaborate in a cosmopolitan
society in which you are not closely
related to most of the people that you
are interacting with and my sense is
that there are many many gaps if you
take any two people there's a question
of how many things unites them and how
many things separate them and what I'm
going to argue is that we need a kind of
maybe a computer science approach to
this in order to understand how we
socially feel that essentially if you
took all of the characteristics that
might unite you or might separate you
each one is a bit that can be flipped in
the direction of affinity or it can be
flipped in the direction of a gap and
that when you encounter somebody you're
dealing primarily with all of the gaps
that's the obstacle to collaboration and
the question is how many of those gaps
are jumpable now you had a quote that
was relevant to this did you want to
read that well it's actually an extended
passage it's it's a few pages from
Sebastian youngers book tribe on
Homecoming and belonging and I don't
know if it should be read before or
after the story that you want to tell
well either way once you start with it
and we'll come back okay so this is this
is I think his latest book if I remember
correctly and it is quite excellent it
was recommended to me about a year ago
by a friend of ours actually the same
man who made the knife behind you and
I've since read and can come to know
some
some of his other work and the man
himself today's veterans often come home
to find that although they're willing to
die for their country they're not sure
how to live for it it's hard to know how
to live for a country that regularly
tears itself apart along every possible
ethnic and demographic boundary the
income gap between rich and poor
continues to widen many people people
live in racially segregated communities
the elderly are mostly sequestered from
public life and rampage shootings happen
so regularly that they only remain in
the news cycle for a day or two to make
matters worse politicians occasionally
accuse rivals of deliberately trying to
harm their own country a charge so
destructive to group unity that most
past societies would probably have just
punished it as a form of treason it's
complete madness and the veterans know
this in combat soldiers all but ignore
differences of race religion and
politics within their platoon it's no
wonder many of them get so depressed
when they come home I know what coming
back to America from a war zone is like
because I've done it so many times
younger rights first there was a kind of
shock at the level of comfort and
affluence that we enjoy but that is
followed by the dismal realization that
we live in a society that is basically
at war with itself people speak with
incredible contempt about depending on
their views the rich the poor the
educated the foreign-born the President
or the entire US government it's a level
of contempt that is usually reserved for
enemies in wartime except that now it is
applied to our fellow citizens unlike
criticism contempt is particularly toxic
because it assumes a moral superiority
in the speaker contempt is often
directed at people who have been
excluded from a group or declared
unworthy of its benefits contempt is
often used by governments to provide
rhetorical cover for torture or abuse
contempt is one of four behaviors that
statistically can predict divorce and
married couples people who speak with
contempt for one another will probably
not remain united for long the most
alarming rhetoric comes out of the
dispute between liberals and
conservatives and it's a dangerous waste
of time because they're both right the
perennial conservative concern about
high taxes supporting and non-working
underclass is entirely legitimate roots
in our evolutionary past and shouldn't
be dismissed out of hand early hominids
lived a precarious existence where
freeloaders were a direct threat to
survival and so they developed an
exceedingly acute sense of whether they
were being taken advantage of by members
of their own group
but by the same token one of the
hallmarks of early human society was the
emergence of a culture of compassion
that cared for the ill the elderly the
wounded and the unlucky in today's terms
that is a common liberal concern that
also has to be taken into account those
two driving forces have coexisted for
hundreds of thousands of years in human
society and have been duly codified in
this country as a two-party political
system the eternal argument over
so-called entitlement programs and more
broadly over liberal and conservative
thought will never be resolved because
each side represents an ancient and
absolutely essential component of our
evolutionary past
so how do you unify a secure wealthy
country that has sunk into a zero-sum
political game with itself how do you
make veterans feel that they are
returning to a cohesive society that was
worth fighting for in the first place
I put that question to Rachel Yehuda of
Mount Sinai Hospital in New York City
Yehuda has seen up close the effect of
such antisocial divisions on traumatized
vets if you want to make a society work
she writes she said to me then you don't
keep underscoring the places where
you're different you underscore your
shared humanity I'm appalled by how much
people focus on differences why are you
focusing on how different you are from
one another and not on the things that
unite us the United States is so
powerful that the only country capable
of destroying her might be the United
States herself which means that the
ultimate terrorist strategy would be to
just leave the country alone that way
America's ugliest partisan tendencies
could emerge unimpeded by the unifying
effects of war the ultimate betrayal of
tribe isn't acting competitively that
should be encouraged but predicating
your power on the excommunication of
others from the group that is exactly
what politicians of both parties try to
do when they spew venomous rhetoric
about their rivals
that is exactly what media figures do
when they go beyond criticism of their
fellow citizens and openly revile them
revealing people you share a combat
outpost with is an incredibly stupid
thing to do and public figures who
imagine their nation isn't potentially
one huge Combat Outpost are deluding
themselves unbelievably brilliant and so
many of that so many lines in there that
could take an hour's worth of
conversation to unpack completely now
right before we went on I noticed that
Matt Taibbi posted something to his
website now it is a for pay post
and I think one needs to think very
carefully about the fact that
journalistic outfits are falling to this
new ideology and the journalists who
intend to say important things are
having to find ways to feed themselves
outside those traditional modes so I
would encourage you all Matt Taibbi has
been absolutely on fire of late and I
would recommend if you all sign up for
his website but I want to read you the
first paragraph of what he just released
just before you do that I believe I
believe he's on sub stack which is an
excellent way for for writers in
particular to to get paid for their
output so he's I think you can find Matt
Taibbi on sub stack yep he is on sub
stack that's what I'm looking at all
right so Matt Taibbi writes it's the
fourth of July and revolution is in the
air only in America it would look like
this an elite sponsored Maoist revolt
couched as a black liberation movement
whose canonical texts are a corporate
consultants white guilt self-help manual
and the New York Times series rewriting
history to explain an election they
called wrong yep oh my god it's it's
terrifying it is awful and it's
hilarious because he's just he's just
nailed it he's nailed it and you know
you have to be able to laugh at it and
you know as people laugh on a
battlefield and all sorts of other
things because that's human nature but
we are faced with something absolutely
incredible and it is the uninvent of one
of the greatest concepts ever devised
which is not to say that America ever
functioned according to its objective we
moved toward it
we fought one terrible war over a race
already we may be headed toward a second
but what is not well understood by I
think almost anyone who is doing this is
one what happens when you take a flawed
but highly functional society like ours
and you break it right there is a sense
and you will hear people say again and
again that we're gonna have to destroy
this thing in order to build something
better and what they don't understand is
what a power vacuum does if they had
gardened if they had tilled up some soil
and they had decided that that was the
key to wiping the slate clean and
planting their crops they would discover
that they had just liberated all sorts
of weeds that
weren't counting on and that it's going
to take an incredible amount of work to
fend them off so we have a worse problem
and I would I would analogize at the
following way I want you to think about
nuclear reactors and in particular I
want you to think about Chernobyl now a
nuclear reactor is not in and of itself
a complex system it's a complicated
system but a nuclear reactor does not
run itself it is embedded in a complex
system of humans the designers who set
the thing in motion
the people who run it the people who
regulate it and you could walk into the
control room of a nuclear reactor and
there are a lot of buttons you could
flip that would not have a catastrophic
effect but you don't know which ones are
which and the Chernobyl story actually
tells us something important for those
of you who don't remember and I would
actually recommend you check out the HBO
miniseries on what happened to Chernobyl
what happened at Chernobyl was a safety
test it was a test designed to make us
more secure and they were going to run
through some systems checks and it
happened that some of those systems
checks set things in motion that caused
the reactor to quickly overheat and
people's tendency to delude themselves
about what they were seeing prevented
them from shutting it down in reversing
course quickly enough and the rest is
history and the point is what we are
seeing in America today is the flipping
of switches in something even more
complex than a nuclear reactor and the
proposals for switches to flip next are
quite frightening now I don't know what
to make of the story of the McCloskey is
this couple that came out in front of
their home with guns and were filmed and
photographed as a as a protest movement
moved through their private street it's
a complex story and you will see it
portrayed in diametrically opposed way
as depending upon which source you go to
either it was white people brandishing
weapons at peaceful protesters because
they were you know looking at the
boogeyman in front of them or it was
people who were flagrantly
frightening them by marching across
private property and threatening to
invade their homes it's very difficult
to figure out exactly what happened what
what appears to be going on now is that
having come to public consciousness this
couple is now a flashpoint for a war
that some people seem to want to start
and if I'm to understand the story
correctly the protesters who were the
ones to trigger this by marching through
the McCluskey's Street are apparently
going to come back and that is not in
and of itself so surprising but what I
understand is that they have asked the
police for help so that presumably they
don't need to brandish weapons of their
own they the homeowners say the
homeowners have asked the police for
help and apparently the police say they
can't help them they have apparently
also contacted they the homeowner say
the homeowners have also contacted
private security and nobody will take
the job I think that's actually not
surprising but here's it's not the job
of security of private security firms to
take any job that comes to them well it
certainly shouldn't come down to it
every single American has the right to
have their their rights protected by the
police and you know as as Sam Harris
points out in not his most recent
podcast but I think the one right before
the one in which he addresses the
statistics surrounding police violence
and race he says that the monopoly on
violence is one of the greatest
inventions that humans have ever come up
with and I have to agree with him on
this so that is a reference to I believe
it's Max Weber --zz suggestion that
government is a monopoly on violence
that is its inherent nature which does
not mean that government is inherently
violent what it means is that a
carefully wielded threat of violence if
you do not abide by the rules is what
keeps people in line and if the rules
are very good then the threat to punish
those who step outside of them
ultimately if you step outside of the
rules somebody with a weapon comes and
they take you away and you go to a court
and you face due process in this country
the possibility of violence implicit or
explicit is what in
that keeps the peace right and you know
if you have let's say flagrantly
violated the rules in some very serious
way let's say that you have assaulted
somebody without cause then somebody
with a weapon they collect you you face
due process and you out you end up in a
prison now that prison is a kind of
violence right those bars that keep you
in are effectively engaged in violence
you can throw yourself at them in order
to engage in your freedom to go
somewhere and it doesn't let you it's
the equivalent of violence but in any
case the point is I find something very
chilling about the McCloskey story I
have no idea who these people are what
they're about but what I do know is that
you and I faced something like this
and I do know us okay what we faced was
you and I you and I hurt for those who
can't see that you just gestured to me
you're talking not to the entire
audience now but right we face something
very much like this you and I at
Evergreen face something like this we're
a mob that was possessed of crazy ideas
about what we were about began to engage
in flagrant violations of the rules and
threats of violence which ultimately
became real violence and our boss the
president of the college happened also
to be the boss of the police because the
police were a campus police force they
were real police not a security force
they were a police force but he was in a
position to tell them stay out of this
which meant that the protection that we
normally have from the police was pulled
out and we were left on our own with a
mob that was clearly hell-bent on
re-educating us and as I've said before
I don't think they know what they would
have done if they had caught up to us
and we had refused to go along with
their description of the world which we
would have so a very dangerous situation
the police refusing to be involved this
is something most people have never
faced and the fact that we are now
seeing that little experiment and
Anarchy that happened at Evergreen being
brought into the wider world where
people who have run afoul of this
protest movement who can be portrayed as
zealots are going to be left without
police protection this is the flipping
of one of the switches in the reactor on
we are all depending you flip the switch
that says I mean what is supposed to
happen if the police refused to help you
and no security force will come to your
aid when you try to hire them what
recourse do you have right one would
think that the recourse would involve
going to a court and saying I have the
right to police protection the police
are not protecting me and you must
insist that they do it by some sort of
court order but we know also that
because this revolution is happening in
a horizontal fashion that the courts are
not immune to it so in some sense that's
which is read for a reason we know that
pulling the police out and making it so
that people cannot get a redress of
grievances in a court is the thing that
will cause this nation to come toppling
down right you cannot have some
populations who have access to a court
and other populations who don't now that
is not to say that access to courts has
been even in our history it has never
gotten to even but if you want to remove
it from some populations and you want to
inscribe that into the core modality
that we have with each other there is no
way that this experiment can persist
right it is not an evolutionarily stable
strategy which means we're headed to a
power vacuum yeah and this this moment
is not as it would have us believe about
redress of grievances it is about rather
the thing that you and I have both been
saying from the beginning about flipping
the tables turning the tables of
oppression correctly identifying that
there has not been equal access to
things like courts and justice from
police in our nation's history does not
validate the conclusion that we shall
change who has unequal access going
forward and that that will make things
right it does not yep and I would say
that if one is going to evaluate whether
or not the protests move it in the
street is about redress of grievances
then you need to think about things I
don't know if the McCluskey's are are
descended from pilgrims
that doesn't sound like a pilgrim name
so the question is in some sense if
these people are having their right to
to be protected by the police eliminated
on the basis that they somehow are
descended or they're as guilty of
slavery as those who help slave
themselves slaves themselves or
something then there's a question about
well are we gonna sort out whose guilt
goes to what depth that's preposterous
it can't happen and so you know is the
solutions are simply incoherent well let
me um let me do a strange thing let me
steal man perhaps the most outrageous
point that Robyn D'Angelo makes in her
book the one that we are all being being
exposed to too much and this is that all
white people are racist we've all heard
this now and I don't know for sure that
it originates with her but but her book
is currently the one that is spreading
most widely and you know we've talked
about it before on this show so the
point is absurd on its face for sure all
white people are racist really but the
trick here is that she has redefined
what racist means and so that's
illegitimate and I think we've mentioned
before that merriam-webster's is the
dictionaries now falling in line with
this redefinition of racism and you know
that's a kind of doublespeak that's you
know the the second form of new language
that Orwell writes about not new speak
but double speak turning turning extant
terms into something that means
something so different that when people
use them no one is quite sure which
meaning they're in tend to be using so
if we side struck the side step that
linguistic trap though that she's laid
for us and say well certainly I know I'm
not racist what the hell is she talking
about
what what she means and I really don't
know that she has anything good faith
about her at all but what she and the
movement means when they are talking
truth is that it's true that people with
white skin do continue to benefit from
the privileges especially historic but
also still contemporary that having
white skin converse that's just that has
been true
and that's true even though class and
geography are often better predictors of
of outcomes than is skin color so we can
all imagine say a poor white girl in
Alabama in rural Alabama versus a
middle-class black girl in Chicago and
ask you know who is more likely to
succeed in this world and it's gonna be
the the black child in this case even
though it is also true that when those
two people are making decisions about
where to drive at what time of night and
what stores to go into and and what
their reaction is if they're driving and
they see police is going to be different
by race
so all of those things can be true and
you know it's it's insane objectionable
reprehensible all of this to call that
thing racism but that is that is that is
actually deplorable right yeah I'd like
to take that word back too but it it
does obscure bizarrely right it obscures
this kernel of truth at the bottom and
now you have people pushing back so hard
against this insane nonsense that they
are also pushing back against the thing
that is true and that's that is going to
be where the divide actually sticks I
think oh it's going to well you know I
put out a video I can't remember exactly
when but I it's called speak of the
devil and the idea was that they are
gonna call forth exactly the racist
beast that they are claiming dominates
the landscape right now by forcing white
people by backing them into the wall
together you're gonna force them to see
things in racial terms and it's not a
surprise what's coming it's perfectly
predictable and it's extremely dangerous
yeah so anyway good job steel Manning
obviously the problem with the analysis
is that we are forced to the last step
it's not that things are racially well
distributed it's not that they have ever
gotten to zero right
we never neutralize the effects of
slavery and Jim Crow and so we don't
even know what the experiment would do I
have a pretty good guess but we don't
know what the experiment would do if you
ever got everybody to the starting line
at the same time and I think it would be
quite equal but what we are told is that
the very fact
of disadvantage that shows up in
outcomes is evidence of racism which is
a cognitive process occurring inside of
the minds of white people we are also
told not only is it there and in need of
immediate challenge but it is incurable
yeah those two things don't go together
yeah no there's I mean there's there's a
bait-and-switch constantly and you know
we can look at this this book that's
insane white fragility book and we can
it's harder to pinpoint the claims of
activists because they'll always say I
didn't mean it then it was you know it's
not what it seems
but the talking about the population
level the systemic the actual systemic
truth of systems that have benefited
people with white skin conflating that
with individual level racism is
something that the movement claims to
understand the distinction between but
is very very happy to do a constant
bait-and-switch between and of course
this this final point that you make the
the idea that not only are you born
racist but if you claim you're not
you're proving that you're racist it
became you are well then you're
obviously racist it's it's I think the
central rhetorical trap of a rhetorical
Kafka trap of the entire book and the
entire movement that any defense of
yourself is taken as evidence that you
are in fact guilty of the thing of which
you are accused yeah
there's no escape and therefore what is
the conclusion of that the conclusion is
you have to do what we say anybody who
understood that you are guilty of racism
inherently because the color of your
skin and who doesn't like that because
who likes racism anybody who agrees with
those things the next question is okay
well then you're an ally aren't you oh
yeah I guess I'm an ally oh well then if
you're an ally what does that mean it
means you have to do what we say which
means you have to take the risk on our
behalf which means you have to go and
punish other people and so it is a
contagious ideology oh it's and it's
it's effective it's adaptive its
horrifying but it's it's effective so I
wonder and maybe you have someplace else
you want to go first but you know how do
how do we bring the vast majority of us
back to a place where we feel confident
enough to speak up against this deeply
divisive deeply unpatriotic movement
that has a few things at its core that
is correctly identifying but that is
overall so dangerous
to to our humanity and to the country as
well that it really needs to be stopped
well I want to do two things and that is
the second of them talk about exactly
what the prescription might be because
you and I have been challenged with the
question well what should we do if this
comes for us and it's been a very
difficult question to answer but it has
caused us to put a lot of thought into
what the answer might be and it's well
worth going there so we will do that but
I want to tell a little story first in
reference to the point I made it earlier
about gaps between people based on
differences demographic and otherwise I
was out with my kids two nights ago
we hopped on these crazy things called
electric unicycles which it's a terrible
name but it's a very fun little device
and we went zipping up to a local park
to see the sunset it's a beautiful park
on a peak and people gather there who
noticed that the sun is shining and want
to go see the sunset so we went up there
and we sat for a few minutes and as we
were getting up to leave we hopped on
our electric unicycles and a black
family came up the stairs into the park
and something that very frequently
happens when you ride one of these crazy
devices happen which is they started to
talk about what they were seeing because
it if you haven't seen one of these
things before it kind of challenges the
mind and you think how does that work
and how did they stay on them and all of
these things so they had questions and
they were clearly talking about these
but they had questions among themselves
you weren't close enough that they were
talking to you couldn't hear them but we
could watch them pointing and talking to
their children and all of this now under
normal circumstances I love nothing more
than to go talk to people who are
curious about these devices and to
satisfy their curiosity and anyway it
results in camaraderie which I like and
under normal circumstances I would have
done it and in 2020 I am finding that
even though I think I have excellent
skills for crossing virtually any gap
and I've never had a problem crossing a
racial gap
I couldn't figure out how to do it
because there is so much new garbage
circulating about what's going on in
somebody's head now these people were
obviously not many gaps away from me
right these were people who live in my
city these were people who looked at the
Sun setting and had the same thought I
did about what to do to go to this park
these people who brought their kids with
them as I had there's all sorts of
reasons that I should have been easily
able to cross this gap and say hey I
noticed you noticing these things and we
could have started the conversation and
it would have been lovely but in 2020 we
are now losing the ability to do that
the amount of suspicion that we have
about other people based on these simple
demographic markers is now becoming so
onerous that we are losing track of who
we are as Americans and it is an
unmitigated disaster in my opinion the
fact is we knew we never accomplished it
we were headed there and we knew where
we were going you know that the recipe
was delivered to us by a founding father
and it's the founding father who showed
up late it was Martin Luther King jr.
and he gave us the recipe which was that
at some point in the future we would
achieve the ability to judge people
based on the content of their character
rather than the color of their skin and
I don't know that we will ever get a
more eloquent formulation of the
objective he didn't think we were there
he was describing a dream that he felt
would occur in the future if we if we
held true to our values and I I believe
he was right and I don't know how it is
that we have now taken that concept and
thrown it out it's it's absurd so in any
case I hope that we can think about the
puzzle and we can say look we should be
able to talk to each other even when
there are many gaps right even when
there are many gaps you can learn to
jump them but not when a gap is a chasm
right nobody can shout across a chasm
it's not possible so well this gap has
been made increasingly difficult to
bridge by others who seek division well
claiming to seek unity and I mean I
think this is this is exactly one of the
things that you and I have enjoyed so
much about traveling outside of our
usual milieu especially you know far
outside of it especially you know not in
in the Western world but in Madagascar
and in Latin America and various places
and you know meeting people there who
are also middle-class and with whom we
therefore share a ton actually probably
more than we do say a homeless person on
the streets in America but once the
class factories also changed and and
you're you're look you're interacting
with people who have grown up in a
different country with different
expectations about what their lives
would be indifferent promises made to
them by their families and by their
governments about how safe and secure
they would they would be and you see
that actually you can talk with almost
anyone you can talk and connect with
almost anyone no matter what the gaps
are and yet here we are within our own
country within our own neighborhoods
finding ourselves walking around with
more suspicion than most of us ever had
before
it is it is reprehensible but this is
being done to us yep
it's being done to us and I want to make
two more points before we get to
solution making there's been a lot of
stuff about the tearing down of
monuments and I made an ironic statement
on Twitter yesterday and got piled on
because people took it literally as if I
was ready to go tear down monument did
you have an emoji I did but it was a
light bulb emoji and I think people were
thinking that I thought put it in your
bio if there's an energy oh it's there
oh really yeah no it's there it's in my
bio but anyway oh I had suggested that
maybe we could all team up on tearing
down the monuments and leave each other
standing which I thought was very clever
because the whole idea of leaving each
other standing is really the core of the
thing and as much as I don't want to
hand over the monuments you know if it
kept Western civilization intact I'd be
up for discussion right but but in any
case you know that's not how any of this
works I do know that's
have any of this works but I thought it
was hilariously funny other people
thought I was serious in any way I want
to talk about monuments a little bit
there are some monuments that are
troubling right some of the Confederate
monuments are troubling maybe they all
are I also find Christopher Columbus
stuff troubling and the reason I find
Christopher Columbus stuff troubling is
that Christopher Columbus is not a real
thing okay there was a guy his name was
Cristobal Cologne and we can talk about
what he did and didn't do a sure as hell
didn't discover a pair of continents
with fifty to a hundred million people
living on them that's not possible maybe
I didn't know I mean that's like that's
like me discovering light bulbs or
something but in any case crystal walk
alone discovered crystal walk alone
discovered the Americas on behalf of
Europeans and that is of course a good
thing I guess if you're European and
it's a disaster if you happen to be
descended from one of the fifty to a
hundred million people who were living
here already so the point is look those
people are Americans too or at least
many of them are they are entitled for
us not to do national myth making around
a figure that was a complete disaster
right national myth making has to
include all of us history is complex but
national myth making really should be
about all of us discovered America
doesn't make any sense
so I'm not a fan of Christopher Columbus
or mythologizing about him but I was
looking at some of this stuff about
Mount Rushmore and I was ready to have
my same eye rolling reaction like I'm
pissed off that they're pulling down
statues of George Washington yes I know
that he held slaves I know that he was a
flawed person I also know that he was a
decent person and that the fact that he
held slaves doesn't say otherwise which
is tragic it should but it doesn't now
what I learned in studying about George
Washington and I don't put this up
against the slaveholding but I do say
this was a complex complicated character
he actually defended Jews in the
colonies I didn't even know there were
Jews in the colony right so he was a
defender of Jews in the
that's an unusual fact about the man he
was also unusually decent when it came
to power George Washington could have
been king if he wanted to people were in
the mindset that they needed a king and
they would have been they would have
made him king gladly
and he refused it multiple times so this
was a complex man and we have to deal
with him in his full complexity but you
know what they're all complex Martin
Luther King jr. there's strong evidence
of plagiarism right he was also I don't
want to use the word philanderer but he
cheated on his wife not an uncomplicated
character but obviously if we're going
to limit the conversation only to people
who have nothing weird in their history
it's gonna be very quiet conversation
right your hero is by very by the very
definition of the term are going to be
people who've traveled unusual paths and
those unusual paths are not going to be
rosy all the way so we have to tolerate
the fact that history is a complex
narrative and we have to deal with the
complexity so well the dehumanization
works both ways I think and by both ways
maybe it won't be clear what I mean just
yet we we see people dehumanizing their
enemies and imagine that they are just
pure evil and that if they have a view
that seems out of step with what is
currently acceptable then they must also
be you know Nazis basically right but
there's also a dehumanization that
happens in the other like valence in
which you know it may be the most famous
version of this that like the archetypal
version of this is the noble savage all
right we have this idea that whoever
existed in advance of the colonial
forces coming in for instance was living
a true and virtuous life on the land in
which they would never have used up all
the resources because somehow the
tragedy of the Commons and all of game
theory and the competitive part of
evolution and the fact that tribes were
meeting tribes populations were coming
up against populations and resources
were scarce somehow none of that applied
we haven't we there's this
dehumanization that imagines that some
people lived a perfect utopia and one
also that imagines that some people are
pure evil and
really the first one is just not
possible right the as much as you know
we've talked about in a number of places
maybe mostly in the book that is still
not out about the Mayan enlightenment
right the a just the extraordinary
number of things that the Maya long
before the the actual of the European
enlightenment happened in in Europe
discovered they had astronomers they had
scribes they had the concept of zero
they had agriculture they had obviously
architecture they had the written word
and they had library's full of books and
their understanding of their universe
was extraordinary and rich and deep and
varied and also throughout the Americas
there was slavery this is before crystal
ball Cologne Christopher Columbus ever
showed up there was slavery and there
was war and there was murder and there
was rape and there was all of these
things because every time you get humans
together this these things will end up
happening and you know maybe maybe we
are at a moment now finally where we are
seriously producing slavery and genocide
but they're not over
they're not over rape they're not right
and imagining that there was any time in
the past any population that was stable
that had that didn't have at least many
of these things is delusional it is
delusional now I do think this is a deep
conversation for another time I do think
there was something different about what
was going on in the Americas than in the
old world at the point that Cristobal
Colon showed up and I think it was
different because the Americas had not
yet become full in other words people
become more brutal as the zero-sum
dynamic set in and so I do think that
there is ironically something about the
native populations that in the same way
that our prosperous nation has been
capable of doing very good things
because it was prosperous because we
weren't resource stressed I do think
that there was something to be gleaned
from what the native populations were up
to and that even the slavery when you
look at it it looks less brutal a lot
less brutal mhm and so anyway that's a
conversation for another time well it's
I mean just
taggart it's a zero-sum versus
nonzero-sum and what kind of frontier
were they engaging in question exactly
exactly
but actually this brings us to this
marvelous example so I was looking at
this I don't know a series of articles
about monuments being torn down and I
was looking at you know the New York
Times waded into the thing with Mount
Rushmore and I was just not feeling good
about where we were headed and I ran
into an article in which a Lakota chief
was saying that we need to tear down
Mount Rushmore and that he would do it
with his own hands right and I was not
in a mood to entertain this argument but
I read the article and I was disturbed
because although I do not for a second
think that we should tear down Mount
Rushmore
I was quite compelled by his argument
his argument was very robust and so I
don't think it really is an argument for
tearing down Mount Rushmore but I think
the point is actually there is a
reckoning to be had over Mount Rushmore
right if ever there was a place where
there was a need for a understanding
that the land was stolen and then
repurposed for a patriotic demonstration
that negates a particular populations
history and that in fact a current
demonstration of American patriotism
that includes fireworks is actually
putting the land in jeopardy right the
land being flammable and these fireworks
being not in keeping with good
stewardship I was compelled that
actually this this was a very strong
argument and that in fact what I would
like to see is us having that in other
words we do need to be involved in a
negotiation over the white the correct
way to go forward from the history of
this Monument now there was also you
know the New York Times was all about
telling us that the sculptor was a white
supremacist which I don't know if he was
a white supremacist but he clearly had
ties to white supremacists he was also
an anti-semite and I thought you know
what okay I have standing in this
conversation he was an anti-semite that
does not for one second make me want to
tear down this Monument right so you
know we're in a complex landscape but it
is one in which there is another way the
involves honestly reckoning with the
past and figuring out how to bring
everybody in on that reckoning and the
final thing I will say is that our good
friend Dave the sword maker who made the
knife behind us pointed me towards an
article in which the there is a statue
in Alaska of Captain Cook and the
question came up of course as it would
in this era what to do about the legacy
of Captain Cook and his compromised
moral standing and the solution was too
high unfortunately I don't have the
article here but basically the village
in Alaska is villages not tribes the
village that is most prominently
affected by the legacy of Captain Cook
that is to say the people who suffered
the most as a result of Captain Cook
were brought into a discussion about
what to do with the monument which seems
to me exactly the right thing it's the
honorable thing and it's the thing that
will allow us to move forward as
Americans together rather than some of
us tearing down monuments that mean
things to other people which is only
going to result in us becoming
foreigners to each other and allowing
the the world to collapse that seems an
interesting approach I hadn't hadn't
heard it it obviously wouldn't work in
most cases certainly in the lower 48 in
general it's much less clear what you
know who who the most affected are by
particular historical figures you know
in Alaska with Captain Cook it's an
easier thing to pinpoint I'm still I'm
still a little bit concerned about the
sort of you know populist solution
making there but in in that case I see a
place for it at least in in the
approaches that might honorably
honorably be taken well you know the
first assignment I ever gave when I came
to Evergreen and started teaching there
the first assignment was for my students
taking evolution all of them for the
first time was to explain what an
apology was I wanted them to drill down
and figure out if they could understand
what an apology was and I said to them
you know an apology is a mystery because
it has tremendous
effect on the way people think about
stuff that has happened to them right
why should it
an apology consists of one individual
vibrating the air molecules between them
and another individual and then a little
membrane in your head wobbles and
proportion and you deduce some meaning
that's coming but if you've been harmed
by somebody why would a wobbling of
membranes in your head in any way serve
to compensate you such that it would
change your sense about whether or not
the thing was okay or not right so
anyway it's a it's a tough assignment
try it that's all well you're stopping
there let's put it this way for those of
you who are ready to hear what I think
the right analysis is an apology is
evidence of a debt in other words if I
have harmed you and I don't acknowledge
it then the debt is in dispute but if I
have harmed you and I say you know what
I harmed you let me tell you how much I
harmed you and what you hear says
actually you do understand how much you
harmed me then you've got two things one
you've got a debt that you can call in
and we know how we know the magnitude of
it and two you have my explicit
description of what I did wrong so if I
do the same thing wrong again the crime
is much bigger because what I've done is
I've said here's what I understand about
that crime and to do it again would mean
I was conscious of the fact that I was
doing it which is a very different crime
it's a premeditated crime so anyway my
point is we need to engage in a
discussion a national discussion in
which the various things in our history
that are not comfortable and not
honorable and not defensible are placed
in proper context and we agree on what
they are and we agree on what's wrong
with them and by doing that we can
actually all move on all of us right and
that doesn't mean that there's no
reckoning of any other kind to happen as
I've said before I am really not a fan
of monetary reparations because I think
we can predict exactly why that policy
would be a disaster but the idea of
investments in communities that are
still suffering the echoes of Jim Crow
and other things seems a very good idea
so anyway at some level informally
that's the proposed
so that a Truth and Reconciliation
approach to the the ugliest parts of our
history is important even you know I
feel like I have taken on American
culture I am born of immigrants as you
are so not you're not the children of
immigrants immediately but I'm descended
from immigrants my my ancestors weren't
here when there was slavery and so you
know in some sense why am I even talking
about it well because I have taken on
American culture so in some sense it's
been imported into my software you know
the downstream effects of that but
anyway that's that's that's about all
that needs to be said about that we go
to solution making yeah we have about
five minutes five minutes yeah so maybe
we should mostly save this for next time
because it itself is a is a long
conversation but let's just get it
started here okay in thinking about what
we keep hearing from lots of people
which is what do I do when it comes for
me right I think the answer can't be it
can't be an individual answer it's not
going to work and what I have begun to
observe is that there's certain
environments online where you can't
navigate this stuff and then there are
others where the structure of the
environment itself allows you to so on
reddit for example reddit is now a
disaster for many reasons but inside of
a subreddit many people can talk about
what's going on and most of the users
are anonymous just by virtue of the way
it works and so my point would be I
think that people who understand that
there's something wrong about the
ideology that's marketing through our
our national landscape and appending
structures on which we are depending
that those people need to be able to
find each other and they need to be able
to have a conversation that functions as
a reality check at first and that
reality check is the key ingredient to
be able to maintain your bearing that is
to say when it comes for you it's going
to be very hard to resist the mob and
what it insists is true in terms of your
defects and it's going to be very hard
not to say the things that it wants you
to say
I would advise you not to say those
things but it's not gonna be possible
for everybody people have livelihoods
they have to maintain people have
children they have to protect but if you
can find a community that is capable of
barring that set of Kafka traps and you
can check in with it and you can say
look I had to go to this training in
order to retain my job and I can't
afford to give up my job but here's what
was said at this training and here's why
I find it absurd and somebody else can
say you know I saw the very same thing
and here's what I thought that reality
check that allows people who are trying
to resist this to just simply not be
each of us alone but to find each other
compare notes and then eventually to
discover things that work what can you
say when somebody says one of these
things that actually causes the script
to change that diverts it for a moment
that detains it that causes it to have
to answer questions that it should have
to answer I believe in there is the
seeds of a solution in which we stop
playing defense which isn't working and
we start playing offense which will yeah
and and you can start collecting people
this way right people who are listening
here presumably already already know
most of this and probably many of you
are being forced to sit in on these
trainings to participate maybe even to
identify your own internal racism
whatever maybe you are in a place where
you can speak up we would hope so
find a place online where you can do
exactly what Brett is talking about and
then go back to the next training may be
a bit emboldened with an idea of how you
can say something how you can just lodge
an idea lodge a criticism that even if
it is not even if it does not make clear
to the people organizing the training or
the or the true believers that you are
in fact lodging a complaint those other
people among your colleagues who also
don't respect what is going on will hear
it and probably at least one of them
will come to you quietly privately and
say yeah me too
at which point you invite them in to
whatever online community you have and
say listen in on this then let us figure
out if we can generate ideas and tools
with which to fight off this thing this
ideology which is not about anti racism
and it's not about inclusivity and it's
not about diversity it is quite the
opposite and then next time you go to a
training again maybe they're now two of
you one person stands up in a row of 30
you'll get shouted down as you did right
as you did Brett but two people there's
a better chance three people what's the
tipping point there will be some tipping
point there will be some tipping point
and it's going to change it's not going
to be a flat percentage in a room of 30
versus a room with 300 it's not going to
be 10% in both places but there is some
number of people in a room that says you
know what no me critiquing the work of
someone is not racist based on whether
or not they have black skin or not no
everyone gets to be critiqued everyone
gets to be congratulated and focusing on
the color of the skin of the person who
I'm critiquing is actually the racist
thing not the other way around
absolutely and as you pointed out when
we initially started exploring this is a
solution one of the things that is sure
to happen if you check in with your
online environment which you may have to
create it may be a slack or a discord or
something you create an environment
where you can safely talk and you can
establish the rules for people coming in
you know good honorable IDW kind of
rules but once you do that and you
establish your reality check and you
figure out what you can say in a
training that will advertise that maybe
you're not quite fully on board you will
find people will come to you and they
will say thank you thank you for doing
that right when you know who those
people are who hear what you're saying
and wish that they were saying it too
you can invite them into these
communities and they can get their
reality check and what that means is
that you will ultimately form a group of
people who understands that something
that isn't desirable is afoot and you
can start figuring out how to back each
other up and you will become safer so I
think that really is the route to a
solution yeah so you said something to
me a week or more ago that
you haven't yet set on air so I'm gonna
say it and see if you want to riff just
just briefly before we we have a number
of announcements and then go to break
before we come back for the QA we should
all be pursuing the moment when if we
were in a movie the hero music would be
playing right we all recognize it when
it happens in the movies we know when
that music is about to start playing and
we know what the character what we want
the character to do we know we want to
be we do so how do we attain that in
life yeah we all know the soundtrack if
they reverse the soundtrack of the
villain and the hero you'd be like what
the hell kind of movie is this what is
this right so we all know what it is
that feels good and we really all know
or most of us know what's right and so
to the extent that something that is
very much not right is afoot the
question is what you know what does the
hero do what is that you know the person
gives the awful fascist speech and the
you know the hero in the back row does
that slow clap thing that reveals that
he's just not buying it that thing the
question is how do you get to that scene
in the movie what needs to be true in
order for you to pull that off it's so
inspiring and we just saw this in peaky
blinders which we just watched again
with our children we watched with our
children yeah yeah
so I guess before we go I would like to
say announcements - yes we will get to
the announcements in a second but we are
in an interesting place with the
articles of unity and the unity 2020
project it is possible but it really is
going to take people willing to engage
the small amount of risk and energy
involved in signing up so that we can
count you and Counting you does not mean
that you are signing up to engage this
plan it means you're listening to hey
Zack could you put up the yep so we will
have the page up in a second but what we
need you to do is follow our Twitter
account if you're on Twitter come check
out the Articles of unity give us your
email address this really can happen you
would be amazed at some of the behind
the
scenes conversations that we are having
but what we need is a groundswell of
people who are willing to be just daring
enough to say you know what I can
envision a different possibility I can
envision inaugurating someone other than
Trump or Biden come January and I would
feel much better if we did so so if
you're willing to go that far we can get
there please please please help us so
this is the site us is not the two of us
us as far bigger than that yep this is
this does not go you sign up here you
write an email here if you're offering
to help it goes to a team of people who
are who are working on this yeah and it
it just might work
it just might work yeah oh can I say one
other thing I need to clean that was one
of the announcements incidentally Oh
awesome taking care of yeah we're
checking stuff off I want to go back
just to I want to make sure people don't
misunderstand my story about the black
family who showed up in the park I got
no sense that they would have had a
problem with me approaching them but the
context of white people approaching
black people in 2020 has grown far too
complex and I think it would have been
fine but it is getting harder and harder
to do that was my point all right what
are our other announcements well right
my trackpad is not working so I don't
have yeah I was trying to find that Mike
I can't I can't do it right so let's
just do the announcements here we now
have a Clips channel for for this main
channel where says that were you going
to show the clip channel
[Music]
and it's it's live as of I think today
or yesterday we've got someone very good
working on making clips he's got I think
clips from episodes 25 and 26 up he'll
start you'll do 27 and 28 shortly and
then go back through at least 19 so
there it is we'll also put a link as we
will to unity 2020 in the description of
this video if you we've made this
announcement before if you are
interested in a private Q&A with us once
I'm in once a month become a Dark Horse
member at my patreon at the $5 level or
up and that Q&A is on the last Sunday of
the month but it's then up for anyone
who's who's a patron to view at any
moment and then actually apropos what
you look we were just talking about with
regard to finding community in our first
private Q&A one of the dark hairs
members made a discord server for us and
it is now up and at the moment it just
has people who were live on that QA but
we are also going to make that available
to patrons at the $5 an uplevel for
either of us right so either patrons of
yours at $5 and up or of mine will have
access to that we don't have that set up
yet but we'll get that within their 24
hours I get an invite yep and and on
there there are I so new discord I don't
really know what's going on but but
there are you know sub conversations
around Unity 2020 and presumably there
you know there will be ways to find each
other if you want to do just what we
were talking about and discuss offerings
and strategies on how to respond to
workplace trainings anything else
excellent I think that's that's it
we will be back in about 15 minutes to
engage your questions with our answers
looking forward to it
you